A Guide to the Hank Wolfe papers, 1918-1981
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Hank Wolfe papers, 1927-1981
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 171
10.4 linear feet
Hank Wolfe
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dinah Wolfe in 1981.
Biographical/Historical Information
Hank Wolfe (12 January 1907 - 3 February 1981), newspaperman and athletic organizer, was born in Baltimore, Maryland. At the age of six, he moved to Richmond, where he remained for the rest of his life. During his youth he issued a monthly newsletter for the Rotary Boys' Club and played on the Club's varsity basketball team. Wolfe graduate from John Marshall High School in 1924 and the Massey Business College in 1926. Following graduation, he worked for the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway and as a part-time reporter for the Richmond News Leader. In 1936, he became a full-time sportswriter for the paper, and in 1947, he became a copy editor. He stayed with the paper for 56 years, retiring in 1978. From 1952 to 1962 he also edited The Reflector, the monthly journal of the Richmond Jewish Community Center.
In the 1930s, Wolfe organized the Richmond Athletic Commission, and for several years, he was the secretary of the Richmond Baseball Commission. He was responsible for the establishment of the Richmond Jewish Athletic Hall of Fame. From 1944 to 1968, Wolfe was State Commissioner of the Virginia Amateur Softball Association. During that time he introduced the use of 10", 12", 14" and 16" softballs in tournament play, a tournament for college teams and one for mixed team play. Because of his efforts as an organizer, the City of Richmond became known as the "Softball Tournament Capital of the World." National Softball Week started in 1951 and the National Softball Hall of Fame proposed in 1956 were his ideas.
Wolfe was a member of Temple Beth-El, the Richmond Jewish Community Center, the American Association of Retired Persons, and the Richmond Institute of Lifetime Learning. He was an honorary member of the United States Slo-Pitch Softball Association. He and his wife, Dinah, had three daughters.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains materials relating to Wolfe's career as a newspaperman and work as an athletic organizer in Richmond, Virginia, from 1932 to 1978. In addition to biographical materials, there are records relating to his service on the Richmond Baseball Commission in the mid-1930s, his membership in the Richmond Newspaper Guild and his organization of the Richmond Jewish Athletic Hall of Fame for 1954-1957. There are lists of Virginia athletic championships maintained by Wolfe and some extraneous pieces relating to sports in Richmond. The collection has one folder of correspondence and contracts concerning Wolfe's employment as a part-time territorial scout for the Cleveland Indians Baseball Club from 1951 to 1961. The bulk of the papers relate to Wolfe's tenure as State Commissioner for the Virginia Amateur Softball Association from 1944 to 1968. There are ten scrapbooks (1927-1966) that Wolfe maintained of his sports column for the Richmond News Leader.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into the following series: Biographical Information, General Sports and Richmond, 1932-1961; Softball, 1942-1968; Scrapbooks, 1927-1981; and Printed Materials, Photographs, and Ephemera, 1918-1980. Materials in each series are arranged topically and thereunder chronologically.
Contents List
- Serues 1: Biographical Information, General Sports and Richmond, 1932-1961
  - Biographical Information, Sale of Sports Library (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence and Contracts, Cleveland Indians, 1951-1961 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Richmond Baseball Commission, 1932-1933, 1955 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Virginia Athletic Championship Teams Lists, 1936-1947 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Richmond Newspaper Guild (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Miscellaneous Richmond Sports Materials, 1936-1952 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Richmond Jewish Athletic Hall of Fame, 1954 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Richmond Jewish Athletic Hall of Fame, 1955 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Richmond Jewish Athletic Hall of Fame, 1957 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Underdog Richmond (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Southern Coach and Athlete, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Southern Coach and Athlete, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Series 2: Softball, 1942-1968
  - Richmond Softball Association, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Amateur Softball (ASA) Hall of Fame (Box-folder 1:14)
  - ASA / United States Slo-Pitch Association Controversy, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - ASA National Championship, 1967 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - World Slo-Pitch Softball Championship (Women), 1961 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Virginia Amateur Softball Association (VASA) (Box-folder 1:18)
  - VASA, 1945 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - VASA, 1946 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - VASA, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - VASA, 1949 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - VASA, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - VASA Forms (Box-folder 1:24)
  - VASA National Championship Bid, 1968 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - VASA National Softball Week (Box-folder 1:26)
  - VASA Photographs (Box-folder 1:27)
  - VASA Programs, 1942-1964 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - VASA Programs, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - VASA Professionalism Threat, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - VASA Publication by Wolfe (Box-folder 1:31)
  - VASA Records (Box-folder 2:1)
  - VASA Men and Women, 1945 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - VASA Men, 1946 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - VASA Women, 1947 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - VASA Men, 1947 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - VASA Men, 1948 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - VASA Women, 1948 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - VASA Men, 1949 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - VASA Women, 1949 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - VASA Men, 1950 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - VASA Sunday School, 1950 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - VASA Women, 1950 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - VASA Women, 1951 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - VASA, 1951 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - VASA Men, 1951 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - VASA Sunday School, 1951 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - VASA College, 1952 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - VASA Central Atlantic Regional, 1952 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - VASA Men, 1952 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - VASA Men, 1952 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - VASA Sunday School, 1952 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - VASA Women, 1952 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - VASA Women, 1953 (Box-folder 2:23)
  - VASA Servicemen, 1953 (Box-folder 2:24)
  - VASA Sunday School, 1953 (Box-folder 2:25)
  - VASA Men, 1953 (Box-folder 2:26)
  - VASA Men, 1953 (Box-folder 2:27)
  - VASA Jewish, 1954 (Box-folder 2:28)
  - VASA College, 1954 (Box-folder 2:29)
  - VASA Men, 1954 (Box-folder 2:30)
  - VASA Men, 1954 (Box-folder 2:31)
  - VASA Servicemen, 1954 (Box-folder 2:32)
  - VASA Sunday School, 1954 (Box-folder 2:33)
  - VASA Women, 1954 (Box-folder 2:34)
  - VASA Women, 1954 (Box-folder 2:35)
  - VASA Women, 1954 (Box-folder 2:36)
  - VASA Jewish, 1955 (Box-folder 2:37)
  - VASA Slow Pitch, 1955 (Box-folder 2:38)
  - VASA College, 1955 (Box-folder 2:39)
  - VASA Women, 1955 (Box-folder 2:40)
  - VASA Central Atlantic Regional, 1955 (Box-folder 2:41)
  - VASA Men, 1956 (Box-folder 2:42)
  - VASA Central Atlantic Regional, 1956 (Box-folder 2:43)
  - VASA Women, 1956 (Box-folder 2:44)
  - VASA Ivitational Mixed, 1957-1966 (Box-folder 2:45)
  - VASA College, 1957 (Box-folder 2:46)
  - VASA Men, 1957 (Box-folder 2:47)
  - VASA Women's Invitational, 1957 (Box-folder 2:48)
  - VASA Slow Pitch Mixed, 1957 (Box-folder 2:49)
  - VASA Slow Pitch Mixed, 1958 (Box-folder 2:50)
  - VASA Women's Invitational, 1958 (Box-folder 2:51)
  - VASA Women, 1958 (Box-folder 2:52)
  - VASA Men, 1959 (Box-folder 2:53)
  - VASA Women's Invitational, 1959 (Box-folder 2:54)
  - VASA Women, 1959 (Box-folder 2:55)
  - VASA Industrial Slow Pitch, 1960 (Box-folder 2:56)
  - VASA Women's Invitational, 1960 (Box-folder 2:57)
  - VASA Industrial Slow Pitch, 1961 (Box-folder 2:58)
  - VASA Women's Invitational, 1961 (Box-folder 2:59)
  - VASA 12" Men, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 2:60)
  - VASA College, 1962 (Box-folder 2:61)
  - VASA Servicemen, 1963 (Box-folder 2:62)
  - VASA 14" Outseam, 1963 (Box-folder 2:63)
  - VASA Men, 1964 (Box-folder 2:64)
  - VASA 14" Outseam, 1964 (Box-folder 2:65)
  - VASA Industrial Slow Pitch, 1964 (Box-folder 2:66)
  - VASA Industrial Slow Pitch, 1965 (Box-folder 2:67)
  - VASA 14" Outseam, 1966 (Box-folder 2:68)
  - VASA Modified Speed, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 2:69)
  - VASA Invitational Mixed, 1967 (Box-folder 2:70)
  - VASA 14" Outseam, 1967 (Box-folder 2:71)
  - VASA Industrial Slow Pitch, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2:72)
  - VASA Invitational Slow Pitch, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 2:73)
  - VASA 14" Outseam, 1968 (Box-folder 2:74)
  - VASA Invitational Mixed, 1968 (Box-folder 2:75)
  - VASA 10" Slow Pitch, 1968 (Box-folder 2:76)
  - VASA 14" Slow Pitch, 1968 (Box-folder 2:77)
  - VASA Men, 1968 (Box-folder 2:78)
  - VASA 4-Ball, 1968 (Box-folder 2:79)
  - VASA 10" Slow Pitch, 1968 (Box-folder 2:80)
  - VASA Women, 1968 (Box-folder 2:81)
  - VASA Trophies, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 2:82)
  - World Open Slow Pitch Tournament, 1953-1959 (Box-folder 2:83)
  - World Open Slow Pitch Tournament, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2:84)
- Series 3: Scrapbooks, 1918-1981
  - Clippings, 1927-1932 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1932-1934 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1934-1936 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1936-1938 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1938-1940 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1940-1941 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1941-1943 (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1946-1945 (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1945-1957 (Box 7)
  - Clippings, 1957-1981 (Box 7)
- Series 4: Printed Materials, Photographs, and Ephemera, 1918-1980
  - Baseball Player Photographs, 1940 (Box 8)
  - Baseball Schedule of Games, 1952-1953 (Box 8)
  - Baseball Scoring Sheets, undated (Box 8)
  - Baseball Tournament Souvenir Programs, 1959, 1961-1963 (Box 8)
  - Boy's Club of Richmond Annual Report, 1924 (Box 8)
  - Coach and Athlete Magazine, 1973 (Box 8)
  - Constitution of the Amateur Softball Association of America, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Football Players Photographs, 1940, undated (Box 8)
  - Handbook of the National Association of Approved Basketball Officials, 1948 (Box 8)
  - Humor Newspaper Clippings, 1974, 1977-1980, undated (Box 8)
  - The Jeffersonian, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Local Baseball Player Newspaper Clippings, 1940 (Box 8)
  - Local Baseball Player Newspaper Clippings, 1940 (Box 8)
  - The Messenger - Boy's Club of Richmond Newsletter, 1922-1928 (Box 8)
  - Methodist Institute Basketball Teams Newspaper Clippings, 1922-1924 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Photocopied Newspaper Articles, 1918, 1921-1924, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Photocopied Newspaper Articles, 1925-1926 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Photocopied Newspaper Articles, 1927, 1949, 1962-1971 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Sport Team Paperwork, 1924-1927, 1946-1947, undated (Box 8)
  - Newspaper Clipping, 1923 (Box 8)
  - Pocket Dictionary, undated (Box 8)
  - Rotary Boy's Club Basketball Team Photographs, 1923, 1927 (Box 8)
  - Third Annual Basketball Tournament Program, 1946 (Box 8)
  - Virginia Jewish News, 1925, undated (Box 8)
  - Wolfe, Hank Photograph, 1935 (Box 8)